<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Nybles</title><description>Taking Bytes out of Information</description><link>http://localhost:2368/</link><image><url>http://localhost:2368/favicon.png</url><title>Nybles</title><link>http://localhost:2368/</link></image><generator>Ghost 1.5</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2017 18:41:56 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:2368/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>A Chat with Divanshu Garg, alumni IIITA working at GOOGLE</title><description>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;h2 id="pleasetellusaboutyourselfintroduction"&gt;Please tell us about yourself: Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi, I am Divanshu Garg. I am an alumnus of IIIT Allahabad from 2015 batch. I obtained my bachelors degree from the institution majoring in Information Technology. After graduating from college, I worked as a Software Engineer at Google Sydney for more than an&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/welcome/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">598896347cedfb23a6b20d20</guid><category>Tech-Talks</category><dc:creator>Nybles</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2017 16:32:58 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/08/14066374_1274383865907838_7132537184792904589_o.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;h2 id="pleasetellusaboutyourselfintroduction"&gt;Please tell us about yourself: Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/08/14066374_1274383865907838_7132537184792904589_o.jpg" alt="A Chat with Divanshu Garg, alumni IIITA working at GOOGLE"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hi, I am Divanshu Garg. I am an alumnus of IIIT Allahabad from 2015 batch. I obtained my bachelors degree from the institution majoring in Information Technology. After graduating from college, I worked as a Software Engineer at Google Sydney for more than an year. Presently, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;I am working in a similar role at Google, Mountain View.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; I am enthusiastic about learning new technologies and building anything cool using them. I am particularly interested in &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;machine learning, competitive programming and Android development.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://scontent-sit4-1.xx.fbcdn.net/v/t1.0-9/18341672_1542443579101864_6099236277731938935_n.jpg?oh=f1c4d78691f69a7a88d1b6beddca17fa&amp;amp;oe=59F9DBE0" alt="A Chat with Divanshu Garg, alumni IIITA working at GOOGLE"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="whatwasyourfirstimpressionaboutthecollege"&gt;What was your first impression about the college?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first day at college is always a memorable event for anyone and IIIT Allahabad made it even more so. I was fascinated by the beauty of the campus and the college infrastructure. The hostel quickly became an eternal part of my life. Right from the first day, I met so many great friends over there who made four years look short. Apart from batchmates, the seniors were also very helpful and provided guidance whenever I needed one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="bestexperienceincollege"&gt;Best experience in college?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘Hostel life’ would be the college experience which I miss the most. The life was so different over there. Staying awake all night doing random stuff, hanging out with friends all day, playing cards for hours and hours, watching movies and the list goes on and on. Parallel to all the crazy fun, the coolest thing about hostel life is that you keep on learning something new every single day without even realizing. The interactions that you have, the group learning efforts you put in - everything contributes to your knowledge bank. No matter how much I want to, it’s almost impossible to get those times back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="whatwasthebestthingyoudidincollegewhichhelpedyougrowinyourlineofwork"&gt;What was the best thing you did in college which helped you grow in your line of work?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the thing which helped me the most was keeping the attitude that you can learn anything if you actually want to. With easy access to an entire world full of knowledge in the form of internet, you can easily start learning new areas and build things that fascinate you. As part of competitive programming, I learned a lot about algorithms and data structures to consolidate my fundamentals over which the world of software resides. Apart from this, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;I expanded my knowledge in different areas like website development, Android development and image processing.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Since I am quite passionate about games, I always tried to blend my learning with my passion. That is the reason why most of my learning projects surrounded around this theme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="howwasyourexperienceinacm"&gt;How was your experience in ACM?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to call my ACM experience a long and beautiful journey. I was introduced to the world of competitive programming at a very early stage in my college life. I began solving problems on various online judges like SPOJ and Codechef. After failing to solve the majority of problems, I came across &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘Introduction to Algorithms by CLRS’.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; The book is really well written. It starts right from the basics and helps you learn thoroughly myriad of algorithms. As my knowledge developed, I could realize that I am able to solve much harder problems and think in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started participating actively in all the major periodic programming competitions hosted by TopCoder, Codechef and Codeforces. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;It’s quite different to actually participate in a competition rather than doing practice.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; The time constraint imposed during the competition pushes you to the limit and some really nice ideas evolve. Once I was well versed with the basics across different topics, I began learning more and more comprehensively about a specific topic at a time. This actually helped in tackling some medium-hard problems in that respective topic. So, the right approach according to me for acing in competitive programming is to begin with a breadth-first approach and shift over to a depth-first approach once you have a good hold over the basics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, the experience changed my attitude towards approaching a problem completely. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;It taught me to be much more persistent and to not give up early.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Even years later, it helps me to gain a much more deeper insight into the problems that I explore today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="whatwasyoursteppingstonetowardsyoursuccess"&gt;What was your stepping stone towards your success?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stepping stone to success in my life was the moment when I was &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;unable to qualify for the ACM regionals in second year.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; It taught me that failure is a perpetual part of success. The only thing to keep in mind is to come out even stronger from a failure. You need to introspect and draw conclusions from every failure and apply them in future to emerge as a better individual. Nothing is a better growing experience than failing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="whatisthebestthingaboutworkingingoogle"&gt;What is the best thing about working in Google?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best thing about working at Google is the people you meet here and collaborate with. Google is well known for recruiting some of the best minds in the industry. To be actually there and work with those minds is absolutely amazing. You meet people who have been in the industry for decades of years who would share their experiences. You meet people who are researchers and have excellent theoretical knowledge. And, you also meet people who are from non-CS background telling anecdote about what fascinated them and diverged their career from some other industry to the programming industry. It is indeed a very rich experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the non-learning front, Google is crazy with all the perks they offer to their employees. They care a lot about employee comfort and providing the best work environment. Quickly I came to realize that a better working environment could actually increase your productivity manifold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="bestplacestolearnaccordingtoyou"&gt;Best places to learn according to you?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The places to learn varies a lot based on the technology or thing that you are learning. In my experience, there is no single place where you can find all the resources that you want even for a single topic. Let’s say for competitive programming, I had to explore across hundreds of different websites, books and references. It’s hard to pick the best out of those since different resources excel at different topics. But on a broader note, I believe learning comes best when you practically do something. Always ensure that you are implementing the things in some form that you learn. In the process of implementing it, you would learn a hundred different more things naturally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="thingsyoushouldntmissincollege"&gt;Things you shouldn’t miss in college?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;College life offers you four years of freedom. This is the time when you should have both fun and learning at its peak. Striking the right balance between the two is a must. The way you invest this time will define your future. You should have loads of fun but at the same time, broaden your knowledge by getting your hands dirty in different aspects of software development. Until and unless you understand the basics of a thing, it’s quite hard to judge whether you are actually fascinated by it or not. Taking a broad bag of knowledge from your college life would definitely help you excel in your career in subsequent years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="whatisyournextcareergoal"&gt;What is your next career goal?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;not a very great future planner. I try to focus on things in the present and how to make the most out of it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Expanding my knowledge is something I always keep focussing on. Currently, learning more about machine learning and its real-world applications is intriguing me. This is also aligning quite well with the work that I am doing at Google which is based around improving search and intelligence efforts in Google Apps (Gmail, Drive, Calendar).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="anyadviceyouwouldliketogiveus"&gt;Any advice you would like to give us?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only advice that I would like to give is &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Follow your passion and work hard to make your dreams come true”. Every person is unique with different interests.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; You should not follow something because someone else is doing it. You should follow something because you have a passion towards achieving it. You will realize very soon that once your interests match with what your goals are, it’s only a matter of time and hard work before you achieve them. Never be afraid to dream big!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://scontent-sit4-1.xx.fbcdn.net/v/t1.0-9/15781648_1411898245489732_5689838117252030605_n.jpg?oh=6118378fa3fc507f37ed540cc5332a88&amp;amp;oe=5A2E619F" alt="A Chat with Divanshu Garg, alumni IIITA working at GOOGLE"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Hackers who changed the world</title><description>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In today's technological age, where harldy anything can be considered safe, it has become far easier to break into someone’s personal zone. By personal, we do&lt;br&gt;
not just mean the social media. The world wide web which has become the hub of storing and restoring information, considered to be&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/the-editor/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">598896347cedfb23a6b20d1f</guid><category>Tech-Knowledge</category><dc:creator>Nybles</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2017 16:32:57 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://casper.ghost.org/v1.0.0/images/writing.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;img src="https://casper.ghost.org/v1.0.0/images/writing.jpg" alt="Hackers who changed the world"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In today's technological age, where harldy anything can be considered safe, it has become far easier to break into someone’s personal zone. By personal, we do&lt;br&gt;
not just mean the social media. The world wide web which has become the hub of storing and restoring information, considered to be&lt;br&gt;
the safest vault, is a mere toy in the hands of a few computer geniuses. Hackers, Black Hat Hackers, villains, crackers,&lt;br&gt;
cyber-criminals, cyber pirates as they are well-known, throw a malicious software or virus at a system to gain access to the&lt;br&gt;
desired information. Piqued by curiosity, they may perhaps break into your system too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://wallpapercave.com/wp/mQJEaae.png" alt="Hackers who changed the world"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From once being the realm of curious teenagers to becoming a mysterious entangle of the arena of government spies, professional&lt;br&gt;
thieves and soldiers of fortune, computer hacking has come a long way in the past four decades or so. To put it in the simplest way&lt;br&gt;
possible, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;hacking&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;is about understanding how things work, breaking them into smaller pieces, fixing their flaws, adjusting&lt;br&gt;
them in accordance to your needs or improving them and finally reassembling them back to their form&lt;/em&gt; and the person engaged in it is&lt;br&gt;
called a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;hacker&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a compilation of a few hackers (or the whiz kids) who put the world in awe with their dexterity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John Draper,&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;the original whistle blower.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A legendary figure within the computer programming world and the hacker and security community, John Draper is the king of what&lt;br&gt;
they called &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;phone phreaking&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; back in the 1970s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While playing with a plastic whistle from a cereal box, Draper and a friend noticed that it sounded a lot like the tone of AT&amp;amp;T's&lt;br&gt;
routing switches for phone calls! Out of that simple discovery came the infamous &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;blue boxes&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; which Draper designed and sold&lt;br&gt;
from his home; &lt;strong&gt;the boxes allowed you to make as many long distance calls as you liked, free of charge.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Without this odd innovation,&lt;br&gt;
who's to say that we wouldn'tbe paying $3.77 per minute for a call overseas?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://usercontent1.hubstatic.com/12012750_f520.jpg" alt="Hackers who changed the world"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bob Gudgel, Jay Dee Pritchard, and John “Captain Crunch” Draper with a bluebox.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Draper went on to link up with Apple co-founder Steve Wozniak (who brought his friend Steve Jobs along), and he taught the two&lt;br&gt;
everything he knew about phone phreaking, which lead to the first business collaboration of Wozniak and Jobs. Draper served&lt;br&gt;
5 years probation once he was finally caught, but he sort of changed the world, don't you think?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alan Turing,&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;the first hacker ever?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A pioneer in the development of theoretical computer science, providing a formalisation to the concepts of algorithm and&lt;br&gt;
computation with the Turing machine, which can be considered a model of a general purpose computer, Turing is widely&lt;br&gt;
considered to be the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;father of theoretical Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Turing believed&lt;br&gt;
there was a better way to archive vast databases of information without needing to employ hundreds of workers to sit and do&lt;br&gt;
the math all day, crafting quite an innovative idea in back in the 1930’s, devising the idea of modern computing before it even existed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://s-media-cache-ak0.pinimg.com/originals/89/55/45/895545cb1bfe78c4f5b2f0540f70fd3d.jpg" alt="Hackers who changed the world"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Statue of Alan Turing at the Bletchley Park Museum, poring over an Enigma machine.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the Second World War, Turing worked for the Government Code and Cypher School (GC&amp;amp;CS) at Bletchley Park, Britain's codebreaking&lt;br&gt;
centre that produced Ultra intelligence. For a time he led Hut 8, the section responsible for German naval cryptanalysis. He&lt;br&gt;
devised a number of techniques for speeding up the breaking of German ciphers, including improvements to the pre-war Polish bombe method,&lt;br&gt;
an electromechanical machine that could find settings for the Enigma machine. Turing developed quite an innovative machine,&lt;br&gt;
known as &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Turing Machine&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, which was responsible for &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;cracking the Nazi encryption system known as enigma, saving more&lt;br&gt;
British lives in World War 2 than any single person&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Essentially &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Turing hacked the Nazi’s, winning Britain the war!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.rutherfordjournal.org/images/TAHC_Bombe.jpg" alt="Hackers who changed the world"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Bombe&lt;/strong&gt; was an electromechanical device used by Turing (and later British cryptologists in general) to help decipher German Enigma-machine-encrypted secret messages.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A person who uses computers to gain unauthorized access to data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is Google's definition of a hacker. That's precisely&lt;br&gt;
what Turing did and by this definition, he could be classified as &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;the very first hacker!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gary Thuerk,&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;The Father Of Spam!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gary Thuerk — a marketer working for Digital Equipment Corporation (DEC), an early computer manufacturer, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;invented spam.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Yes, you&lt;br&gt;
read the right. On May 3rd 1978, 26 years ago this week, Thuerk composed an email marketing campaign promoting DEC’s newest&lt;br&gt;
computers and sent it to nearly 400 email users on ARPANET — at one time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.adpushup.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/First_spam_email2.jpg" alt="Hackers who changed the world"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The first ever spam mail.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thuerk, however, prefers the term &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E-marketing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;spam&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and claims there's a difference. While it's true&lt;br&gt;
that Thuerk's spam which was essentially a targeted e-mail sent to a specific mailing list, 600 users with a single click,&lt;br&gt;
isn't exactly the spam we know and hate today, he is still the one who had the brilliant idea. He was the first to see a&lt;br&gt;
huge opportunity in online marketing and grabbed it with both hands. A rather &lt;em&gt;unique&lt;/em&gt; way to hack the world indeed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aaron Swartz,&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Internet's Own Boy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will be incredibly inspired by the genius and the drive of Aaron Swartz, humbled by his inner moral code that never&lt;br&gt;
wavered, the courage he had to fight the established corporate machine, and saddened by the loss of a brilliant, gentle soul&lt;br&gt;
who had already had a profoundly positive impact on our lives, yet less than it should have been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I realised there were real, serious problems, fundamental problems that I could do something to address, I didn't see a way to forget that.&lt;br&gt;
-Aaron Swartz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aaron Swartz – ‘The internets own boy’ was a computer programmer, entrepreneur, writer, political organizer and Internet  hacktivist.&lt;br&gt;
He either founded or was instrumental in Reddit, Creative Commons, the RSS Feed and so much more.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aaron was driven by a strong moral code of right and wrong and realized very early in his life that he could make a difference and that if he could, then he should.&lt;br&gt;
One of his defining features was his curiosity – more than just curiosity – his inner sense to always question and challenge everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://s-media-cache-ak0.pinimg.com/originals/ce/3e/fa/ce3efa026f0147ef0907cedc5c024afd.jpg" alt="Hackers who changed the world"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aaron Swartz is a hacker that truly changed the world and helped sculpt the culture of the Internet as we know it today!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="moviestowatch"&gt;Movies to watch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0168122/"&gt;Pirates of Silicon Valley&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3268458/"&gt;Internets Own Boy Aaron Swartz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/k4m4/movies-for-hackers"&gt;More movies for hackers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>IIIT Allahabad Tech Diaries</title><description>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;h1 id="iiitallahabadtechdiaries"&gt;IIIT Allahabad Tech Diaries&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2017 is off to a great start, and we at IIIT Allahabad have been very busy living up to our name as the &amp;quot;Centre of Excellence for Information Technology&amp;quot;. Open source, competitive coding, capture-the-flag tournaments, and many quick talks to get people coding: you&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/using-tags/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">598896347cedfb23a6b20d1e</guid><category>Tech-Knowledge</category><dc:creator>Nybles</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2017 16:32:56 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://casper.ghost.org/v1.0.0/images/tags.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;h1 id="iiitallahabadtechdiaries"&gt;IIIT Allahabad Tech Diaries&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;img src="https://casper.ghost.org/v1.0.0/images/tags.jpg" alt="IIIT Allahabad Tech Diaries"&gt;&lt;p&gt;2017 is off to a great start, and we at IIIT Allahabad have been very busy living up to our name as the &amp;quot;Centre of Excellence for Information Technology&amp;quot;. Open source, competitive coding, capture-the-flag tournaments, and many quick talks to get people coding: you name it, we've done it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="1quicktalks"&gt;1. Quick Talks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quick Talks powered by Github were a means to spread knowledge about upcoming topics among the college students, all done within the easy-to-handle 30 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vishnu K.S., gave a quick talk on his experiences with Open Source development and to inspire people to get started with Open Source development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gautham Santhosh, Co-ordinator of the FOSS Wing, unfurled the complexities of a chatbot and built a fully functioning one within 30 minutes, which was a sight to behold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abhishek Deora, co-ordinator at Geekhaven (our technical society), enlightened us all with him making a game in 30 minutes using the p5.js platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chaitanya Yadav, founder of the startup BitNotes, went all out on how to go from zero to deploying an actual website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IIIT Allahabad has been one of the biggest proponents for getting women to code, with a Code Queens event coming up this Aparoksha (specifically for women) and Neha Kandpal (Member of the Web Development Wing, Geekhaven) delivering a Quick Talk on Web Scraping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Himanshu Shekhar, Member of the FOSS Wing, Geekhaven delivered a powerful talk on how to supercharge the humble VIM text editor, and made everyone wonder how the humble CLI editor became a Sublime-toppling monster, with all functionality one could think of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aseem Shrey, member of the Cyber Security wing, Geekhaven, explained various website vulnerabilities with a step-by-step demonstration of a website being hacked in real time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://geekhaven.github.io/quick_talks/"&gt;View more&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="2opencode"&gt;2. OpenCode&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/fossiiita/opencode/master/Logo.png" alt="IIIT Allahabad Tech Diaries"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A month long event, Opencode, was held by the Free and Open Source Software Wing of Geekhaven to get more people involved in open source development. It was a Google Summer of Code style event, which witnessed great participation (mostly from first year students) and got everyone to think about the vastness and breadth of open source.&lt;br&gt;
For an in-depth analysis of the event, do visit &lt;a href="https://gauthamzz.github.io/2017/02/23/opencode/"&gt;Gautham Santhosh's blog post on it.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="3trihackercup"&gt;3. TriHacker Cup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give the first years a well-deserved taste of various fields within programming, the TriHacker cup was held this year as well, with many rounds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Competitive Coding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Android app development with Graphics Designing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Capture-the-flag tournament&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Web Development and Open Source (yet to be held)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preliminary workshops were held by the respective wings to ensure everyone had a thorough idea about the events beforehand.&lt;br&gt;
There was a roaring response from the rookie programmers with various teams shining in a different events. Overall, it was a great event with the effect of having fully initiated the first years into programming, and having given them enough experience for them to now choose their own arenas within software development; and to get acquainted with the rigor involved in doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="4workshops"&gt;4. Workshops&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Various workshops were held on the currently &amp;quot;in&amp;quot; topics such as Android App Development and working on Github (and git in general), so that the students could get an in-depth view and to expand their horizons in their particular areas of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>A chat with Aditya Chaturvedi, Alumnus, GSoC '14, Amazon</title><description>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please tell us about yourself!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://scontent.fdel1-2.fna.fbcdn.net/v/t1.0-0/p206x206/15697606_1241292349294990_3376205851355482696_n.jpg?oh=e66a334c91af898f6c3f0bb870852745&amp;amp;oe=592BFC5D"&gt;!image&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello, I am Aditya Chaturvedi. I am a IIITA alumnus from 2015 batch. I was from Information Technology batch. During my college days, people knew me more as the guy to call when the internet doesn’t work. Gaming community knew me as F@&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/managing-users/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">598896347cedfb23a6b20d1d</guid><category>Tech-Talks</category><dc:creator>Nybles</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2017 16:32:55 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/08/11088525_830060017084894_4887556929900399052_n.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/08/11088525_830060017084894_4887556929900399052_n.jpg" alt="A chat with Aditya Chaturvedi, Alumnus, GSoC '14, Amazon"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please tell us about yourself!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://scontent.fdel1-2.fna.fbcdn.net/v/t1.0-0/p206x206/15697606_1241292349294990_3376205851355482696_n.jpg?oh=e66a334c91af898f6c3f0bb870852745&amp;amp;oe=592BFC5D"&gt;!image&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello, I am Aditya Chaturvedi. I am a IIITA alumnus from 2015 batch. I was from Information Technology batch. During my college days, people knew me more as the guy to call when the internet doesn’t work. Gaming community knew me as F@LCON. Currently, I am working as a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Software Engineer for Amazon in Bangalore&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What was your first impression about the college?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first time when I arrived in college, I was fascinated by the campus. The buildings, the well maintained gardens, the hostel, it all felt amazing. Just in a few days, I fell in love with the atmosphere around. It was first time I was interacting with people from different places in India and being part of the community felt great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best experience in college?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me the best experiences in college involved sitting on the divider which ran through our boys hostel campus at 2am at night enjoying tea and snack with friends. We used to have a lot of fun and interesting discussion which made the hours fly fast. This was my regular favorite in college. Other than this, the most interesting experiences were as a part of Audio Lights Club (renamed the Acoustics and Media Society) and INDEM. The fun and frolic was all there, specially during Effervescence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What was the best thing you did in college which helped you grow in your line of work?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I always wanted is to &lt;strong&gt;learn things that help me bring my ideas to life&lt;/strong&gt;. This aspiration quickly lead to me learn web development when I joined college. After class hours, I used to spend few hours everyday to learn HTML and PHP and soon I was creating my own website, writing small apps, a dummy twitter etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This aspiration grew more when I started understanding how I can share my creations with other people. This lead me to become curious about web servers which subtly drove me into the field of networking. I joined the INDEM club and learned as much I could on how the Internet works. Along with this, I was also a member of Geekhaven which provided me a platform to write apps for various events around the year specially during effervescence. This exercise of applying computer science to make products soon became a habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started looking for applications for things I read and learn which made learning far interesting. Whether it be Software Engineering or Automata, my primary goal used to be to understand where and how it will be useful. Till day this practice helps me in my day to day work. A few days back I used state machines in automata to help explain User interface interaction design to an intern I am mentoring at work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During exams, I never bothered to finish the course. On retrospect, this turned out to be fruitful because I gave sufficient time to comprehend whatever I studies before moving on to the next topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://scontent.fnag1-1.fna.fbcdn.net/v/t1.0-9/577389_614030262021205_584297965_n.jpg?oh=968dc9e6438730bc847ef447582ca4c6&amp;amp;oe=5967ED38"&gt;!image&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Aditya Chaturevdi And His Team Conducted IIITA's First Mozcafe&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How was your learning experience in GSOC?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GSoC&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.google-melange.com/archive/gsoc/2014/orgs/wikimedia/projects/apexkid.html"&gt;(Project Link)&lt;/a&gt; was a fantastic experience. During my time, the road to GSOC was completely unexplored and we (I, Rahul, Jatin and Charul) were kind of the first passengers to explore this land. We had no idea on how to start and what to aim for which lead us to explore different options. We started reading blogs and articles and chatting on the GSOC mailing list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With hard work and luck we all were able to get selected for the program. It was very exciting. We all celebrated it by sharing some sweets (I remember vaguely) in the football field. GSOC was a the perfect fit for me because it gave me opportunity to apply my knowledge to real world problems. I was fortunate to work with Mediawiki foundation (which powers Wikipedia) and work together with one of their senior engineers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned how professional software development is managed specially when everyone is working remotely. There was no office, no labs, no teams, no hierarchy, just some passionate individuals working together for the good of all. GSOC taught me about Git, Bug boards, importance of documentation in code and outside, gather requirement from users before building a feature, how to get consensus about conflicting points and most importantly how to ask for help when in trouble. The last point helps me till date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When working in a professional environment, it is a skill which must be mastered because the challenges will be hard and individual capacity is limited. Knowing how to be a team player brings the best out of you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What was your stepping stone towards your success?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe the stepping stone for success is the simple idea of &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;working towards something you like without worrying too much about the future&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. I think what worked for me is that I was never obsessed with placements and used my time in things I enjoyed. This belief made me use my time and energy in college clubs like &lt;strong&gt;INDEM&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Geekhaven&lt;/strong&gt;, learning new programming languages and frameworks and going past the traditional “competitive programming” domain which was the norm of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Interviewer's comment: It still is the &amp;quot;norm&amp;quot;, though the tone set by seniors like Aditya sir himself has seen an upward rise in the number of students moving past &amp;quot;Competitive Coding&amp;quot; and exploring new avenues in programming.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe everyone has aptitude towards something unique and if all tried to master the same thing, then the percentage of failures will be higher. Therefore, it is important to recognize your aptitude and utilize it constructively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the best thing about working in Amazon?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: One thing that Amazon thrives on is the open work culture and ownership. Amazon has an environment where hierarchy is mostly symbolic. Here, anyone can question anyone. The concept of “follow the senior guy” is generally frowned upon here. Amazon expect people to do work on their individual level and do not accept things on authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes the environment a lot more open for youngsters because it provides a sense of valuableness. The other good thing about working in Amazon is the fast pace software development cycle. Unlike many other companies, all the ownership of software development fall upon teams of two or three. From taking requirements from the customers to deploying and testing code is handled by the team owning the software. As an engineer this practice helps growth by exposing the person to all aspects of the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best places to learn according to you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What engineering college quickly teaches a person is that one does not need a teacher and a classroom to learn new things. I believe every student, consciously or unconsciously, realize this phenomena after the first semester and it is brilliant because it makes you the master of your own learning. To improve learning the simple formulae is to leave your comfort zone and fail a lot. Failure is the best teacher. One who doesn’t fail hasn’t taken sufficient amount of risk. So move fast and break things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Things you shouldn’t miss in college?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fun. Fun. Fun. And I cannot emphasise it enough, Fun is a no miss. College life is special and short. Use your time judiciously. Memories and friends last longer than few extra pointers. Find your friends, your passion and most important yourself. College is a time to explore and break free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do things you always want to do. Gain different kinds of experiences, learn new things, meet new people, understand them and their ideas. Use your college to not only grow vertically but as well horizontally. A balanced approach in college will prepare you well for the future. Do not over do anything. Also, don’t waste your college time intoxicated, it is already very short.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://scontent.fnag1-1.fna.fbcdn.net/v/t1.0-9/1380248_553871524703746_1615441057_n.jpg?oh=504e43b544736610ad4e7db8a263993a&amp;amp;oe=596209B6"&gt;!image&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Sunburn At effe 2K14&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is your next career goal?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven’t planned anything as of now for my next career goal. Frankly, planning is a myth for me. My long term dream is to start a company of my own and I believe the dots will just connect somehow. Entrepreneurship is inline with my approach to look to bring ideas to life. Another reason for going towards this path is the gut feeling I have towards doing something which helps take the country forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel we have been very fortunate to be educated from one the prime institutes of the country. It is incumbent upon us to contribute towards nation building so that the less fortunate also get a chance to grow and attain a better quality of life. It is true that we are a nation of the poors. Lets try our best to make this false for our future generations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would like to talk to me about anything, reach out to me on &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/zeek102"&gt;facebook&lt;/a&gt;. All the best!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Hackathons: What’s all the fuss about and why you should care</title><description>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/08/hackathon-presentation.jpg" alt="hackathon-presentation"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="whatinsevenhellsisahackathon"&gt;What in seven hells is a hackathon?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you love the sound of clanking of a hundred keyboards? Do you love to be in a high stressed time-crunch environment? Do you love to be at a place with too much tech quotient in a single room? Are you ready to&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/themes/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">598896347cedfb23a6b20d1a</guid><category>Hackathons</category><category>Tech-Knowledge</category><dc:creator>Nybles</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2017 16:32:52 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/08/hackathon-bigpic-1.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/08/hackathon-bigpic-1.jpg" alt="Hackathons: What’s all the fuss about and why you should care"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/08/hackathon-presentation.jpg" alt="Hackathons: What’s all the fuss about and why you should care"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="whatinsevenhellsisahackathon"&gt;What in seven hells is a hackathon?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you love the sound of clanking of a hundred keyboards? Do you love to be in a high stressed time-crunch environment? Do you love to be at a place with too much tech quotient in a single room? Are you ready to feel the thrill of all this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, by now I thoroughly sound like a cliched tourism agent. Let me break it down for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;hackathon&lt;/strong&gt; (also known as a &lt;strong&gt;hack day&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;hackfest&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;codefest&lt;/strong&gt;) is a design sprint-like event in which computer programmers and others involved in software development, including graphic designers, interface designers, project managers, and others, often including subject-matter-experts, collaborate intensively on software projects. Occasionally, there is a hardware component as well. (&lt;em&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;br&gt;
Mumbo-jumbo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;hackathon&lt;/strong&gt; is a programmer’s &lt;em&gt;marathon&lt;/em&gt;. A &lt;strong&gt;hackathon&lt;/strong&gt; is a developer’s &lt;em&gt;Olympics&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
A &lt;strong&gt;hackathon&lt;/strong&gt; is an event where all kinds of permutations of programmers, developers, designers and tech enthusiasts can team up to build something, anything taking their idea from a synapse in their brain to the hands of users worldwide in a few days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="howdoibenefitfromahackathon"&gt;How do I benefit from a hackathon?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m gonna list the benefits down for you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try something new:&lt;br&gt;
Ever thought of making that app but not having enough people to test it and give you feedback?  Ever thought of making that drone but did not have the motivation or the perfect team to help you out?&lt;br&gt;
That is what you get in a hackathon, an opportunity to showcase your skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Build your network:&lt;br&gt;
A hackathon can be the largest gathering of enthusiasts just like you, eager to try their hands on something new. You get the opportunity to meet up with the big shots of the tech industry, the seasoned bearded developers, and the programmers who wear the same shirt everyday and connect with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acquire industry skills:&lt;br&gt;
If you’re novice in programming, you’ll learn how to create a project from scratch, chalk out the problem, and present to a panel of judges. You get an opportunity to enhance your team collaboration and presentation skills.  In short, a hackathon prepares you for working in a fast-paced environment and gives industry professionals experience tackling coding challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Free food:&lt;br&gt;
Now I think I have your attention. Yes, you get free food from &lt;em&gt;Granola bars&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Biryani&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Pizzas&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Coke&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/08/hackathon-food.jpg" alt="Hackathons: What’s all the fuss about and why you should care"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swags:&lt;br&gt;
Okay, you envy that guy roaming around in a &lt;em&gt;Google&lt;/em&gt; t-shirt. Come to a hackathon and be prepared to get a ton of stickers, shirts, etc from all the companies you could have only dreamt of.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2017/08/hackathon-swags.jpg" alt="Hackathons: What’s all the fuss about and why you should care"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work with APIs:&lt;br&gt;
Most companies like Twilio, Spotify, etc that partner with hackathons offer their APIs for the hackers to use free of cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Win:&lt;br&gt;
I know you just rolled your eyes. Look at the prizes of any hackathon and you’ll definitely want to participate in one. And now you’re thinking, “But there’s no way I’m gonna win!”.&lt;br&gt;
Well, there’s only one way to find out isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boast:&lt;br&gt;
After the hackathon, you get to boast about the swags, the project and the people you met in the hackathon.&lt;br&gt;
Heck, you can even turn your project into a full blown product for the world to use!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="arethereanyprerequisites"&gt;Are there any prerequisites?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this is a very subjective question and depends on the hackathon. Some hackathons require you to be an established developer to even participate. But most hackathons allow amateur developers and programmers who are willing to explore new domains and have some idea and want to try it out.&lt;br&gt;
Still, let me list down a few of the prerequisites for you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Willingness to participate:&lt;br&gt;
Trust me you’re not gonna survive 36 hours of coding, building and brainstorming if you’re not mentally prepared and enthusiastic about the hackathon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basic technical skills:&lt;br&gt;
You need to make a project with a usable interface so you do need some basic technical skills so that you can learn advanced things during the hackathon and apply them immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Urge to win:&lt;br&gt;
What’s the point of doing anything half-heartedly? Participate to make a mind-blowing project. Participate with the aim of captivating the judges. Participate with the confidence to win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what are you waiting for?&lt;br&gt;
Get DuckDuckGo-ing for upcoming hackathons near you.&lt;br&gt;
Or let me just save you the trouble by telling you that there’s a hackathon, India’s largest student-held one, organized in one of the top institutes of India. (Hint: Hack In The North, IIIT Allahabad)&lt;br&gt;
Get. Set. Build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>